TOEI COMPANY, LTD. Presents
HAWK OF THE NORTH
One-Eyed Dragon Masamune
TOYOTOMI HIDEYOSHI WAS THE
GREATEST WARRIOR IN JAPAN.
HE TOOK ON THE TASK OF UNIFYING
THE LAND, TORN BY CIVIL WARS.
BUT IN NORTHEASTERN JAPAN,
WARS STILL RAGED ON.
THERE WAS ONE ESPECIALLY
DARING YOUNG WARRIOR.
HE WON EVERY BATTLE HE FOUGHT...
HE DEFEATED SOMA'S FORCES.
FUKUSHIMA'S FORCES.
HE ATTACKED AND CRUSHED
THE OUCHI FORCES.
AND THEN, SET HIS EYES
ON HATAKEYAMA'S LANDS.
ABOUT THIS TIME, TOYOTOMI
HIDEYOSHI WAS IN KYOTO.
-Ieyasu is an eyesore
and Hojo is an internal pain.
They make me gloomy enough,
and now I have a swelling on my thigh.
-A swelling on your thigh?
-Date Masamune.
-He's only a country youth
and poses no threat.
Ieyasu is coming to pay his
respects when his castle is built.
So, Hojo and Date will swear allegiance, too.
-Don't be so sure.
Date may join hands with
Hojo and challenge us.
Oba is Date's neighbor.
Transfer him out and put someone else there.
-Who, Sire?
-Let me see...
-What? Oba-dono is being transferred?
-Yes.
-Who is coming in his place?
-I do not know, sir.
When his castle is completed Tokugawa Ieyasu
is coming to Osaka to meet
with the Kanpaku (Regent).
-Meeting with the Regent?
Ieyasu-dono has made his stand clear.
-If the usually prudent
Tokugawa has forsaken him,
Hojo won't last long.
-Meaning, we should do as Tokugawa does?
-Not exactly.
Our situation is different.
Tokugawa's lands lie between
those of the Regent and Hojo.
-But we are being watched continually...
Nikaido, Ashina and Satake.
They are all the Regent's
trusted right-hand men.
Hatakeyama and Oba were
the only ones who weren't.
And Oba is being transferred.
If the wrong man comes,
a serious situation may arise.
-Lord Tamura's messenger came!
-Tamura's messenger?
Where's Masamune?
Call Masamune!
-Hey! Hold it!
Can't you see?
Get off the horse and put them back!
You have no manners, samurai?
If you haven't, then you're
not a man, but a beast!
-What are they for?
For firewood of course!
-Are you taking them far?
-I'm taking them to the Hakuja
Hot Springs beyond this pass.
Thank you.
It's the first time I've passed
here without a load.
-You live at the spa?
-Just a little further on.
Not used to these roads, are you?
You must be thirsty.
Hungry, too.
It may not taste very good,
but do you want to try it?
-I'll eat it all.
-Go ahead.
You helped me so I'm not hungry.
Any good?
-Very good.
-A samurai who likes millet.
You show some promise.
You may go far one day.
-Will I? How far?
-Let me see...
If things go well, you may even
become a lord.
If you do become a lord,
what will you do first?
-I'll gain more land.
-Fool!
Don't become a lord with such ideas!
-No?
-No!
You would have to fight to gain more land!
Then fields would be wasted
and houses burned!
War hits the masses most!
-But I must fight if a war is forced on me.
-In that case, yes.
Fight wars to end wars.
Make the country peaceful
as soon as you can.
-Old man, I'll take them down for you.
Your lunch tasted good. Thank you.
-If you like millet rice so much,
you can come anytime.
That's Hakuja Hot Springs.
-It seems to be a peaceful place.
-It seems a wounded snake
bathed in the spa there.
That's how it got its name.
-My lord! My lord!
Your father wants you!
-Why?
-Lord Tamura's messenger came!
-What?
-No, no...
Tamura-dono's message was about marriage.
-Marriage...?
-He wishes you to marry his Princess Mego.
-We've lived together for a
decade since your mother died.
Life becomes cut and dry without women.
It's time you married.
A clan lord needs a wife.
Doesn't he?
-That is correct.
Tamura Kiyoaki is a descendent
of Tamuramaro, a great general.
It is a good match.
-I won't.
-Why not?
-I will not be a political tool.
-What? Will you explain?
-Yes.
Tokugawa-dono has abandoned Hojo.
Tamura-dono is Hojo's kin.
It is clear why he wishes a
marriage with our Date family.
-You are very harsh.
-I hate father for using me as a pawn!
What do you think?
-You may be right, Young lord.
-Don't call me that!
My real reason is different
from what I told father.
-What is your real reason?
-I'll tell you.
It is because the girl is bound to be ugly.
-Oh, my!
Kojuro should teach you
not to tease your nurse.
-I'm not. It's the truth.
-Princess Mego is arriving in a day or two.
See for yourself.
-She is?
-Yes. Outwardly, it is to
accompany her father to Odawara.
She will stop by here to see you.
-I won't see her! I won't!
-Young lord, please show her your hawk.
-A hawk in the castle?
-Would you like to see it?
-Yes, please show me.
-It's the finest hawk in Japan.
-Please come.
-She's very beautiful.
-Yes, this is the first time I've
ever seen someone so beautiful.
-My sister expects you to apologize.
-There are always exceptions.
-She will not take excuses.
-Nurse is stubborn.
-I, Katakura Kojuro, agree with my sister.
I'm in favor of the match, too.
-Who said I would marry her?
-She is ideal for you.
-Yes, she's almost too perfect.
-Why not, then?
-My life will be a stormy one,
and I will not live to a ripe old age.
-Wada Nariuki?
I believe he is the lord
of Nagahama Castle.
-Yes, with a fief of 13,000 koku.
-He is not a great lord,
but he has power behind him.
-You wish to see me?
-Wada Nariuki has replaced Oba-dono.
-Wada Nariuki...
I heard that he is Ishida Mitsunari's kin.
-Regent Toyotomi is behind Mitsunari-dono.
-Wada has been sent as their spy.
-They may have worse plans than that.
-What do you mean?
-He may stir up trouble.
No matter who our neighbor is,
our road stretches straight ahead.
-Masamune...
-Don't worry, father.
I know your pet theory!
A warrior's best method
is to win without fighting.
-Put it into practice.
As long as I live,
I will try to avoid wars.
-But in the long run,
we may have to fight at times!
-There you go again!
That reminds me...
What answer shall I give to Tamura-dono?
-I already declined.
-That's awkward.
Even if you refuse
Lord Tamura said he wouldn't
take the princess back...
-That's his privilege.
When is Wada Nariuki-dono coming?
-Sir! He has passed Utsunomiya.
-Farmers! You're in the way!
-Go on, move it!
-What is this?
-A boundary line!
-Boundary line?
But this is Lord Date's land!
-Insolent fools!
Men like you force us to make it
clear that it is Lord Wada's land.
Step back!
I said stand aside!
I warn you not to wander
around here after this!
Look at that sign!
DO NOT CUT TREES WITHOUT
PERMISSION - LORD WADA
-What does it say?
-You are not to touch Lord Wada's trees!
You will be punished if you do!
Do not even touch the
leaves without permission!
-We have no firewood!
-It has always been Lord Date's land!
-Clear out!
-He made his move?
-Fight, if you must?
-No...
Wada Nariuki knows what an
outrageous thing he's doing.
He wants trouble between us.
Then Kanpaku-dono can act.
I have a plan.
Call Yamagami.
-Sir!
-It's the truth! Listen up.
Look at this! How about it?
-What does it say?
-Lord Date's orders.
Move to his land by April 6th.
He'll give each of you land and
exempt taxes for a whole year.
An entire year with no taxes.
How does that sound?
-Sounds like a dream!
-No, and this is the proof.
-I'm grateful! I'll get ready to move!
-Wait, you can't go!
It's against the law and you'll be punished!
-I don't care. I'd starve to death here.
I'll go and see for myself.
"MOVE TO LORD DATE'S LAND BY APRIL 6
AND TAXES ARE EXEMPT FOR ONE YEAR"
-One hundred and forty five people came,
but one hundred were caught.
I believe about three hundred
more wish to come.
-I see.
What will Wada Nariuki report to the Regent?
-There's a forest fire near the boundary line!
-Was it arson?
-The farmers must have done
it to rescue their friends!
-The farmers were tricked
by the promise of land,
and the exemption of taxes!
-Wait!
You said they were tricked?
-Yes, I did.
-Is that your word or your lord's?
Think carefully before you reply!
The farmers are the mainstay of this country!
I'll overlook it if you didn't mean it.
But, if you speak for Wada-dono,
I can't excuse it!
You said they ran away, but
do you know the law about that?
Those who run away will be punished!
And, also the clan from which they flee!
Be careful, or you'll advertise
your failure to other clans.
-My lord, I'm sure he's
acquainted with the law.
-What? Are you saying he is?
-Yes.
The farmers didn't run away.
They were on Date land.
Weren't they?
-Yes.
-I see.
It was my mistake.
-I see. You may go.
-Mitsunari, it seems you
lost in the battle of wits.
He slapped your face and
then sent me this hawk.
A bold youth.
Like the sender, it must be watched, too.
Well, Mitsunari...
I am beginning to get worried.
-Sir?
-Jurakudai has been
built to my satisfaction.
The only thing left is to gain
the reins of government.
I have an eyesore.
-That swelling?
-Yes, there's a youth in Oshu who
can even make Ishida Mitsunari froth.
I'm worried about it.
I'm very worried.
-My Lord!
My Lord!
-Gen'an!
-Yes, sir.
-Will I ever see you again?
-Of course you will, My lord.
But the wound must heal first.
So both eyes must be bandaged
to shut out the light for a while.
Please keep the room dark for a while.
-Who's there?
-It is I.
-Father!
-Does it hurt?
-Yes, a little.
What did Gen'an say?
-He said it's not serious as
long as the wound heals.
The men searched to see if
any proof had been left behind.
But they found none.
We know who is behind it,
but we're helpless.
I wish we had caught at
least one of their men.
I regret it very much.
-Please...
-I thought all you needed was a
tongue and a nose to taste food.
But the eyes are important, too.
Tea doesn't taste good when I
must rely on my memory for its color.
-That's because I didn't make it well enough.
Please rest now.
-Nurse.
-Yes.
-You're not hiding anything from me?
Is my eye hopeless by any chance?
-Young lord.
Of course not
-I see.
It's started to rain.
I can hear the raindrops.
Nurse...
-Young lord?
-I wish to go out.
-Yes, sir!
-The irises must be pretty.
I can't recall the color of the flowers...
no matter how I try.
-I can't tell him.
He has a stout heart,
but he's only 23 years old.
It would be cruel to tell him.
-It's worse to not tell him
he'll be blind in one eye.
-Then you tell him.
I don't have the heart to do it.
-Is it alright to be out in the light?
-My heart feels light again and
I just can't stand being cooped up.
I never thought nature could
be as beautiful as it is now.
I can't imagine how lovely
it would be with both eyes.
-Joy and sorrow differ with one's lot.
Happiness is where the heart finds it.
-Young lord...
The doctor is waiting.
-I'll know today when the bandage comes off.
-I'll take your bandage off
the day after tomorrow.
-Day after tomorrow?
It's sooner than I expected.
-Wounds heal quickly when one is young.
-I see.
Nurse...
-Young lord.
-Tell father!
-Yes!
Young lord!
-Go away! Get out!
-Young lord! Why...
Why did you take the bandage off?
-Nurse...
you knew and you didn't tell me!
-Forgive me!
-Father, Kojuro, everyone knew!
Only I didn't know!
-Young lord...
-What are you staring at?
Do you pity me so much?
Go away!
-Young lord...!
-Get out!
Did you think I'd be sad if you told me?
You thought I was that weak?
You fool!
I'm not sorry about my eye!
I'm bitter because no one told me!
It makes me seethe inside!
Nothing can defeat me!
I'm not afraid to lose an eye!
I lost an eye but the Date Clan is safe!
I won't lose...
-He's stayed in his room for 20 days
now. He won't let anyone near him.
-He won't even talk to Katakura.
-Did you see his eye?
-No.
-Would you like to go hunting?
I hear the hawk you
caught is ready to hunt.
-Father, why didn't you tell me?
You said happiness was of the heart.
Why didn't you tell me that I'd be blind?
-Forgive me...
I just couldn't tell you.
-I'm bitter because everyone kept it from me!
-Masamune!
-What's the matter?
Are you ill?
Do you want some water?
-Go!
Begone!
-Thank you for coming.
-Old man! Old man!
-Oh, you're that...
-Give me some millet rice.
-I thought so.
What happened to your eye?
A fight?
You big fool!
Your parents gave you your body!
Don't abuse it!
But I'm glad it wasn't both eyes.
Now, let's go to my house and
I'll feed you some millet rice.
Tie your horse here.
-Welcome back!
-You know him?
-Yes, I met him at the pass earlier.
-I see.
These days, young people move fast.
This is Chi yo, my granddaughter.
This samurai is...
By the way, what is your name?
-Masanosuke.
-Masanosuke?
Hey, Chi yo... He likes millet rice.
Give him a lot.
Go ahead and eat.
You must be used to
poverty to like millet rice.
What is it?
-I must work first or it won't taste good.
-See?
-I'm sorry I shouted at you earlier.
-I was frightened.
-He fights even if he loses an eye.
What about the horse?
-It's alright. I fed him.
-Did you find him?
-Sir... We only know that he rode
past the Otakemura Highroad.
-Search thoroughly!
-Yes, sir!
-What was that song?
-It's the weeders' song.
-It's interesting.
-The money for the horse.
-Give it to the old man.
-Yes.
-Where is he?
-He went to work.
-I see.
When did your parents die?
-They were killed five years ago.
-Killed?
-During the civil war.
-Your father wasn't a samurai,
so why was he killed?
-Because he didn't hand over any rice.
But he really didn't have any.
So he was finally...
Iran as fast as I could
to my grandfather here.
-You hate wars then?
-Yes.
-Do you hate samurai?
Be frank.
-I hate them!
-Wait!
-Yes, sir.
-Look at all the horses!
-Please return with us.
-No!
-You must.
-Kojuro...
I've begun to see
what I never saw before.
I see with my one eye what
I didn't see when I had two.
I must probe it more.
Leave me alone for a while.
-This hawk does not like me.
Well, Mitsunari, are you ready to attack Hojo?
-Yes, sir. Eight daimyo, including Tokugawa...
They are ready to attack with
a total force of 300,000 men.
-It will mean the end of
the illustrious Hojo family.
Don't stir up trouble.
It'll look like we're worried
about the Date Clan.
-Supreme lord.
-There's no hurry.
-But he's a continual eyesore.
-And he only has one eye.
-I regret that my men failed to kill him.
-Watch, while I kill Date with
the same sword that kills Hojo.
I must have a showdown with him.
Either I kill him, or I
win him over to my side.
-Do you hate the men
who made you like this?
-Yes.
-But you're to blame, too, for fighting.
Aren't you?
-Why side with him?
-We wouldn't have met
if you had both eyes.
Are you angry?
I'm sorry.
-You caught one!
Too bad.
What are you thinking about?
-I'm so confused.
-About what?
-About you, Masanosuke-san.
I was afraid of you at first, fighting and all.
But not now.
You wear nice clothes, have a
horse and swords, but no money.
And those samurai came yesterday.
Who are you, anyway?
Please tell me the truth.
-Why do you ask?
-I'd like you to stay.
Do you want to?
-Chi yo...
I'd like to remain here.
-Masanosuke-san...
-Hey! Hey!
We have guests!
-The samurai from yesterday?
-Chi yo, Chi yo... you'd better not go!
-Young lord!
-What brings you here?
-To visit you, Young lord, of course.
-Thank you.
-I am glad you are well now.
-I have become a one-eyed man.
-I hear it has opened
up new worlds to you.
-Why did you bring her here?
-How can you say such a thing?
The princess has come a long way.
You have not said a kind word to her,
yet hint for her to leave.
I can't stand it!
-It is I who can't!
You and Kojuro are meddlesome.
I declined to marry Princess
Mego from the beginning!
-But I have chosen you for my
husband ever since I met you.
-Mountain roads are bad.
Go back before it gets dark.
Nurse, take her.
-Young lord! Young lord!
-What is it?
What happened to Chi yo?
-She left, My lord.
-Where'd she go?
-To her aunt's house in Mito.
My lord... Please wait, please wait!
Please don't go!
I'll feel sorry for her
if you bring her back.
A lord and a mountain girl...
it would only end in tragedy!
Please! I beg you not to go!
-My lord, the Regent is marching
towards Odawara!
-What?
-Please return!
My lord! You must not think only of yourself.
The fate of your vassals and
people rests on your shoulders.
You cannot avoid it!
-What's the Oshu badger doing?
The time has come to
get rid of the swelling.
-This is no time to think!
Take your men and join
the Kanpaku-dono's forces.
-Yamagami... How many days to Odawara?
-Sir. At least ten days.
-Ten days?
What about the Regent's forces?
-They have passed Okazaki.
-We're too late.
-We must hurry and join him.
He will pardon us if we
go before Odawara falls.
-My lord, there is no need
to fear the Regent so much.
If Kanpaku-dono forces us to,
we will fight like Oshu samurai.
-No, no. I wish to avoid a war which
would involve and kill my people.
Masamune, what is your opinion?
-There is no need to go to Odawara.
-You will fight the Regent?
-No, Kanpaku-dono will not wage war on us.
-What?
-He's after Hojo.
So he won't attack us.
If the Regent is the man I think he is...
He will not fight us.
-That may be so.
But to be absolutely safe,
it would be best to join him.
-Reporting! The Hatakeyama
forces have invaded our land!
-What?
-Don't retreat! Attack them!
Don't retreat!
-Send his man back
and defeat Hatakeyama!
-But he says Hatakeyama
will bow to our conditions.
-Conditions?
War is not a business transaction!
It is either smash, or be
smashed by the enemy.
-Yes, but there are many
ways to smash the enemy.
The best way is to win without
shedding unnecessary blood.
-No, unless we kill Hatakeyama,
he will always be at our throats!
The sacrifices will be greater if you wait!
-You don't know how a liege lord should act!
-I'd rather not know!
-Quiet!
How dare a son of mine say that!
You cannot call yourself a lord
if you forget the people's welfare.
-Father, we must kill him for our
people's welfare and to stop wars.
-Hatakeyama isn't as
important as the Regent.
We must go to Odawara.
What if we make the fatal error of being late?
-Father, why do you curry
favor with the Regent?
-I'm not!
But he has the help of Heaven.
Why do all the clans gather about him?
It means ruin to defy Heaven's will
and disappoint our people.
-I have agreed to all your conditions.
Please take a look.
-Thank you.
-Then...
-This is an outrage! Guards! Guards!
-Stand back!
I'll take Lord Date as hostage
and wait for a new truce.
-Shoot me and keep the
Date honor unsullied!
Shoot me!
-Wait!
My lord! My lord...
-My lord...! My lord!
My lord... My lord...
Hatakeyama took your father!
-Damn it!!
-My lord.
-Father!
-My lord...
-Father... Father, forgive me!
I had to uphold the honor of our family!
Kojuro, hang Hatakeyama
up for three days and nights!
-Masamune, the Date name is
untarnished because of you...
I am very happy.
-Kojuro... Kojuro are you here?
-Yes.
-Prepare to leave for Odawara!
-Yes, sir.
HONJIN
(Headquarters)
-They're keeping us waiting.
They've made us wait for three days...
It's outrageous!
-Our fate depends on it.
So let's be patient.
-Sagara reporting.
-How is the Oshu hawk?
-Calm and composed.
-He only has one eye,
but he has keen perception.
Mitsunari, shall I see him?
Masamune, are you bitter
towards the man who did that?
-I was.
-You were, but are not now?
-Yes.
I understand things better with one eye.
If I had both eyes...
I'm afraid we would never have met.
-You may be right.
-Kanpaku-dono...
The man who failed to kill me...
Do you not think he
is very bitter about it?
-He is Lord Date, the mighty daimyo.
-Only one eye, but a fine lord.
THE END